<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://jessemackinnon.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://jessemackinnon.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-06-04T22:09:34-07:00</updated><id>http://jessemackinnon.com/</id><title type="html">Jesse MacKinnon</title><subtitle>Random writings from a film and history nerd.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Black Panther Primer</title><link href="http://jessemackinnon.com/2018/02/black-panther-primer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Black Panther Primer" /><published>2018-02-14T08:28:31-08:00</published><updated>2018-02-14T08:28:31-08:00</updated><id>http://jessemackinnon.com/2018/02/black-panther-primer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jessemackinnon.com/2018/02/black-panther-primer/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2018/Who-Is-The-Black-Panther-1302x1000.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the forthcoming release of Black Panther, I’ve been excitedly reading through the prominent titles and and writers who have defined T’Challa over the past 50 years. While my survey has yet to be completed, I can provide a decent overview for people fascinated by the character and are interested in learning more about him.
&lt;!--more--&gt;
Black Panther was created by Stan Lee and Jack Kirby in 1966, debuting in Fantastic Four #52. He was the first black superhero in American comics, and was quickly given a spot on the Avengers. The first title that focused on him exclusively was the unfortunately named Jungle Action. Written by Don McGregor, it introduces Erik Killmonger, one of the Panther’s chief antagonists, and details the nation of Wakanda. This series is irreplaceable for what it contributed to the lore of the character, and McGregor’s dignified characterization of T’Challa. However, during the first plot arc, he clearly has to balance the kind of exploitation that audiences might expect from “Jungle Action” with his desire to write a serious title. The second plot arc comes closer to that, with the Panther fighting the Klan in rural Georgia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon thereafter, Jack Kirby wrote and illustrated the Panther’s first self-titled series. Unfortunately it’s clear that Kirby was more interested in surrealism and experimentation than he was in actually fleshing out the character. Given the iconic status of Kirby in comics and the importance of the character he created, it’s surprising that this entry in the character’s history is so lackluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McGregor reunited with T’Challa in the 1988 &lt;a href=&quot;http://a.co/j85sDZS&quot;&gt;Panther’s Quest&lt;/a&gt;. Originally published in Marvel Comics Presents, this storyline details the Panther’s journey to apartheid South Africa to learn the whereabouts of his mother. He is quickly waylaid, and spends most of the title fighting the evil regime. This is a very gripping series, because the atrocities detail therein are too horribly real. McGregor’s meticulous structure gives the title as much gravity and weight to match any of the iconic entries that was written at the time. But unlike the gritty comics that defined the era, Panther’s Quest seriously tackles one of the great atrocities of the time, while not letting itself merely wallow in endless despair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://a.co/cdxFlOo&quot;&gt;Christopher Priest run&lt;/a&gt; is the cornerstone of the character. Priest himself had started his career in comics as the first African American editor of a major studio. In his 5 year run, Priest charges headlong into both the lore of Wakanda, and American racism. Here’s an illustrative example. Early in the run, T’Challa’s State Department liaison, Everett Ross, takes him to a State Department function in NYC. When T’Challa realizes the his delegation are the only black people in the room, Ross contacts African American community leaders in the city. They organize an impromptu gathering of people eager to catch sight of the famous African King. However the NYPD soon arrive to disperse the “riot.” Black Panther intervenes to protect the innocent assembly… and the Avengers are called in to support the Police. Priest directly questions the role of superheroes in supporting a racist status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that also characterizes Priest’s tenure is how he writes T’Challa differently from other superheroes. Most capes are fundamentally reactive. They wait until a villain or calamity befalls them, and then solves the problem. Priest turns this formula on it’s head. T’Challa may have great strength and agility, he may have a Vibranium suit, but in the Priest run his real power is being able to predict his opponents. Ross is the audience character, and much like Watson in the Sherlock Holmes stories, the Panther stories end with Ross learning how T’Challa had predicted his foes and prepared to entrap them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The narrative style of the Priest run is very much in the edgy, MTV inspired meta-narration that characterized mid-90s Marvel. But nevertheless, his entries have my highest recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005, filmmaker Reginald Hudlin began his run on the title. The first six issues, &lt;a href=&quot;http://a.co/dHTZtWs&quot;&gt;“Who is the Black Panther?”&lt;/a&gt; is his contemporary retelling of the Panther’s origins in the present day. If you’re looking for an easy entry into the lore of the Black Panther, here is a good place. Also look for the introduction of Shuri, T’Challa’s sister, who has become a central part of Wakandan lore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main reservation about the Hudlin run at large isn’t something I dislike about the author’s style, it’s what I dislike about Marvel in general. Their overeagerness to create a vast, interconnecting world often dilutes the impact of the individual title. This run was frequently interrupted by events that had little to no impact on T’Challa or Wakanda, from House of M to Civil War. I also have large reservations about his decision to make T’Challa marry Storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major Hudlin contribution is his WWII prequel, &lt;a href=&quot;http://a.co/2JVjH1g&quot;&gt;Flags of our Fathers&lt;/a&gt;. In it, the Nazis attempt to invade Wakanda to secure its Vibranium. Captain America is dispatched to assist the Black Panther of that era, but finds that the efforts of his Howling Commandos are largely unneeded. Again, this is excellent exposition to someone new to the title, and pretty exciting to boot. (My great hope for the Black Panther film is that the big cameo will be Chris Evans in flashbacks.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next on my list to read is Black Panther: The Man Without Fear. So updates to come…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next several years, Wakanda was used as Marvel’s pin cushion, and frankly it’s bullshit. We have all these neutral to evil fictional countries and kingdoms like Latveria. But when it came time for villains to give a good solid sucker punch to the good guys, they chose to devastate Wakanda. Pick another punching bag, Marvel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all gets picked up by Ta-Nehisi Coates. Without doubt, his &lt;a href=&quot;http://a.co/21XH2PT&quot;&gt;“A Nation Under Our Feet”&lt;/a&gt; is one of the best runs of any comic I’ve ever read, in no small part due to how he concludes the drama, so I won’t spoil it. The major downside is that it is not ideal for entry level readers. This was the first Black Panther comic that I bought, and I actually had to put it down for several months while I got caught up on the mythos. Depending on how much exposition the film will contain, this title might actually wind up being a decent follow up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a.co/jbfWsMg&quot;&gt;World of Wakanda&lt;/a&gt; is a title that takes place contemporaneously to the Coates run, and details the Dora Milaje, the all female organization that functions as the Panther’s bodyguards and elite defenders of Wakanda. Written by Roxane Gay, it functions as a compelling love story as well as indispensable world building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that Black Panther works the best when it’s like Star Trek. An adventurer from a futuristic society solves problems and battles injustice on his travels. The twist is that his futuristic society is an African nation that resisted European conquest, and and the injustice he fights is all too frequently American.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very happy to have added Black Panther to my comics collection. Wakanda Forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/2018/tchalla-king-of-dead.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2018/tchalla-king-of-dead.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jesse</name></author><category term="Black Panther" /><category term="Comics" /><category term="Marvel" /><summary type="html">With the forthcoming release of Black Panther, I’ve been excitedly reading through the prominent titles and and writers who have defined T’Challa over the past 50 years. While my survey has yet to be completed, I can provide a decent overview for people fascinated by the character and are interested in learning more about him.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Discovery: Context is for Kings</title><link href="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/10/discovery-context-is-for-kings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discovery: Context is for Kings" /><published>2017-10-02T23:43:40-07:00</published><updated>2017-10-02T23:43:40-07:00</updated><id>http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/10/discovery-context-is-for-kings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/10/discovery-context-is-for-kings/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/context-is-for-kings.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prologue is over. The Pilot has arrived.
&lt;!--more--&gt;
Context is for Kings focuses on our protagonist she is impressed into service on the Discovery. And I will say, after the moral ambiguity of the prologue episodes, it was very refreshing to see some unambiguous heroism depicted on the show. (And reciting Lewis Carroll while doing it. Goddamn.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that Nicholas Meyer was not just a hire to appease the fanboys. The show features scientists running wild experiments and are critical of the more militarized aspects of Starfleet’s mission is a key aspect of the show. Not to let the future installment of the films cloud our judgement, but in The Wrath of Khan, the Genesis device is presented as something that is mostly positive until perverted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something else to consider is how Discovery is also reaching back to an important source that inspired Star Trek. AE van Vogt wrote novels and stories that featured the kind of near omnipotent adversaries and super-men that were encountered frequently by the original Star Trek crew. Even Q and Nagilum from Next Gen are ripped directly from his pages. The stories set on the Beagle feature a ship, crew, and story structure that was definitely a defining example of the space opera genre. Now in Discovery we see a beast that is consuming people, and maybe a little bit more. The design seems to be inspired by Coeurl from Black Destroyer, and for the sake of our crew, I hope the screen version is not nearly as intelligent as his resemblance to his short story counterpart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/2017/black-destroyer-215x300.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/black-destroyer-215x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a stark break from tradition that the Captain not be the moral center of the show. But when looking for broad indications of what the show is going to prioritize, security chief Ellen Landry is billed as a guest star rather than a headline lead. Instead, I think the character arc of Cadet Sylvia Tilly is going to be a significant focus for what the moral center of the show is. She doesn’t let the fact that she’s a bit of an outcast dampen her ambition or her earnestness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could Lorca be lying about the astromycology experiments? Well, he did show Burnham some glimpse of the technology in action. The alien was probably something that the Glenn had inadvertently brought back from a distant world. The biology lab that it is ultimately stored in has a Gorn skeleton in a display case, and what appear to be Cardassian Voles on the table, so I’m going to assume that it’s not related to the top secret experiments. Also, if Lorca really is looking for a biological weapon to use against the Klingons, he’s got the perfect sitting on his desk. Duh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things I want from the show: I want to actually take time to breathe, and register the emotional reactions of the characters more. I will say that if the “black badges” turn out to be Section 31, I am totally getting off this ride. Starfleet Intelligence is fine. But a secret organization is not secret if everyone is talking about them. But for what it’s worth, “black research” has historically involved experimental avionics in the Air Force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Universal law is for lackeys. Context is for kings.” There we have it, a key theme for the show. I’ve given Kurtzman a lot of flak in the past, but a recent interview with him stands out: “For me, at the core of ‘Star Trek’ is the idea that Starfleet’s mission is to understand the other, or what is perceived as the other. To use a word that may seem ironic, our approach was to humanize the Klingons, meaning we know a lot about them. In a moment when we are living in a world where ideologies are so polarized and polarizing, what I did not want to do was just make them the bad guys. I was not interested in doing that version of the show.” The notion that we need more knowledge and to expand our understanding seems critical to what Star Trek is to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/2017/discovery-ship.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/discovery-ship.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jesse</name></author><summary type="html">The prologue is over. The Pilot has arrived.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Puerto Rico is an American Colony.</title><link href="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/puerto-rico-is-an-american-colony/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Puerto Rico is an American Colony." /><published>2017-09-30T13:45:17-07:00</published><updated>2017-09-30T13:45:17-07:00</updated><id>http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/puerto-rico-is-an-american-colony</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/puerto-rico-is-an-american-colony/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/Ponce_Massacre.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few reminders about the history and political status about Puerto Rico:
&lt;!--more--&gt;
With the Carta Autonómica, Spain had given Puerto Rico the capacity to govern itself. Elections were held, with a new Parliament being seated on July 13, 1898. The Americans invaded on July 25. A press release by the McKinley State Department stated, “Once taken it will never be released. It will pass forever into the hands of the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The American investors were promptly given control of the Bank of Puerto Rico. The Foraker Act structured the government in such a way that the Governor of Puerto Rico would be appointed by the President of the United States. Education was restructured, with classes conducted entirely in English, with Spanish treated as a special subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1899, a hurricane hit, and property taxes were exponentially increased. Most landowners were forced to either sell their property, or seek American financing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puerto Rico’s diversified agricultural economy was transformed into a monoculture of sugar plantations. Local plantation owners could finance their operations only via local banks which offered high interest rates, compared to the low rates that American companies received from the commercial banks in Wall Street. This factor, plus the tariffs imposed by the US Congress, forced many of the local sugar plantation owners to go bankrupt or to sell their holdings to the more powerful American sugar companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/08/06/opinion/free-puerto-rico-americas-colony.html?mcubz=3&quot;&gt;the New York Times in 2015&lt;/a&gt;, “The most unfair law of all is the Merchant Marine Act of 1920… which requires that every product that enters or leaves Puerto Rico — cars from Japan, engines from Germany, food from South America, medicine from Canada — must be carried on a United States ship. A foreign-flagged vessel may directly enter Puerto Rico — but only after paying taxes, customs and import fees that often double the price of the goods it carries.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 2, 1917, President Woodrow Wilson signed the Jones Act. While it did further democratize the government of the island, most fiscal and economic matters remained subject to Washington’s approval. Their new citizenship meant that Puerto Ricans were eligible for travel to the United States without a passport. It also meant that, when Congress passed the Selective Service Act two months later, conscription was extended to the island. 20,000 Puerto Ricans were drafted during World War I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything resembling pro-Independence activism was ruthlessly crushed. For example, on March 21, 1937 the Nationalist Party organized a peaceful march to commemorate the anniversary of the end of slavery in Puerto Rico. Under the orders of the US appointed governor at the time, police fired into the crowd, killing 20 and wounding hundreds more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1948, the American governor instituted the Ley de La Mordaza. This made it illegal to fly the Puerto Rican flag, or publicly express support for Independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1950, the Nationalists staged an uprising, which coincided with an assassination attempt on President Truman. Insurgents succeeded in seizing the town of Jayuya. The government responded by leveling the town with P-47 Fighter Bombers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 1952, the Constitution of Puerto Rico was instituted, organizing the island as the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico. Shortly thereafter Operation Bootstrap was organized to industrialize the island. Governor Marín enticed US mainland investors to transfer or create manufacturing plants by granting them local and federal tax concessions, and with the promise of a worker base that could be paid much lower than in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1960s, the FBI and CIA conducted COINTELPRO projects in Puerto Rico to investigate, undermine, and discredit the Independence movement. According to FBI Director Louis Freeh, “there had been egregious illegal action, maybe criminal action, by the FBI in Puerto Rico.” Over 80,000 suspected Independence activists were under surveillance, and any method was used by the FBI to disrupt their lives, whether that was breaking up marriages, getting them fired, and otherwise discredit them in the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Nations established the Special Committee on Decolonization in 1961. They immediately called for Puerto Rico’s independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even into the 21st century, suppression of Puerto Rican activists has persisted. In 2006, Filiberto Ojeda Ríos was killed in his home by the FBI. While the FBI defended their conduct during the raid, the Civil Rights Commission of the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico determined that it had been an “illegal killing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1976, Congress altered the tax code, allowing American companies to operate in Puerto Rico without paying corporate taxes. But in 2006 they closed this loophole, causing a massive flight of capital from the island, plunging it into its current recession. The entirety of debt is owned by Wall Street banks, but due efforts by the late Strom Thurmond, American bankruptcy law has been amended to exclude Puerto Rico from Chapter 9 bankruptcy protections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, the US Congress created PROMESA to restructure Puerto Rican debt. This has included measures such as shutting down hospitals to send the money that would otherwise be spent funding them to Wall Street banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puerto Ricans have increasingly been turning out in periodic referendums in favor of Statehood, with over 60% of Puerto Ricans favoring it in 2012. Of course the next step in the process of Puerto Rico would be Congressional action. But given that the Republican Party has grown increasingly hostile to Hispanic people, they are not eager to admit a state that would likely vote Democrat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to recap:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puerto Ricans are taxpaying citizens. They can travel to the US without a passport. They pay income taxes to the Commonwealth, who in turn pool those taxes and pays them to the US Federal Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Puerto Ricans are entirely disenfranchised in the American political process. They do not send Representatives or Senators to Washington. They cannot vote for President. Their only avenue of participation in the national political process is voting in the Democratic and Republican Party Presidential Primaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their economy has been devastated by over a century of American economic exploitation. 45% of Puerto Rican citizens live below the poverty line. The unemployment rate on the island is 12.4%. And virtually the entirety of their industry and economic resources are owned by mainland American corporations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The natives are a uneducated, simple-minded and harmless people who are only interested in wine, women, music and dancing.” -New York Times, 1899&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Such poor leadership ability by the Mayor of San Juan, and others in Puerto Rico, who are not able to get their workers to help. They want everything to be done for them when it should be a community effort.” -President Donald Trump, 2017&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jesse</name></author><category term="Imperialism" /><category term="Puerto Rico" /><summary type="html">A few reminders about the history and political status about Puerto Rico:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Star Trek is dead. Long live Star Trek!</title><link href="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/star-trek-is-dead/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Star Trek is dead. Long live Star Trek!" /><published>2017-09-26T10:40:09-07:00</published><updated>2017-09-26T10:40:09-07:00</updated><id>http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/star-trek-is-dead</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/star-trek-is-dead/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/Spock_funeral.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve watched the opening episodes of &lt;em&gt;Star Trek: Discovery&lt;/em&gt; twice, and I’m heartily on board. There’s something fundamentally relieving about having &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; on the air again.
&lt;!--more--&gt;
There’s a lot to love: Adventures on the edge of space. The current iteration of the Klingons seem very topical to challenges facing us today. Moral dilemmas. I was entirely on board with the three leads, and Sonequa Martin-Green’s Michael Burnham in particular. A Federation that places its ideals of peace and exploration at the forefront.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But ultimately the show is saddled with heavy fan expectations. It is the &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; series with the most weight on its opening since &lt;em&gt;The Next Generation&lt;/em&gt; thirty years ago this month. Even on the nascent Internet in the early 90s, memes still occasionally popped up calling Picard weak, and scoffing at what was was perceived to be an inferior iteration of the franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time has not been kind to that interpretation. While the first season is borderline unwatchable, Picard and his crew’s adventures have a lasting, transcendent quality that has by far outstripped the original. And in most &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; fan circles, it tends to be the baseline for how most committed Trekkies think the franchise ought to be. Most look at the cerebral quality of the show and how Picard was committed to diplomacy and understanding as the quintessential quality at the heart of &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any logical analysis of the last few films of the series can tell we are very far from that. Why? How did we get here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something to examine is &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt;, and how it affected superhero comics. Comic books reached a very sterilized form in the 1950s, and it took several decades for them to reclaim any measure of sophistication. By the 1970s emotional depth and narrative complexity were heartily returning to the medium, yet they were targeted at and marketed to young people. &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; was not a straight rendition of the superhero mythos. It was a dark, ironic spin on it. “What would Batman’s sex life be like?” It’s critical reading of the genre resonated with people, and the adult oriented story kept pace with its aging fan base. The problem it created was that the classic characters from other books don’t work as grim antiheroes. But due to the success of &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt;, most titles strived to match that grim and cynical aesthetic. The deconstruction became the culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same has largely held true for &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Deep Space Nine&lt;/em&gt; is heralded among fans as the unappreciated gem of the franchise. While its contemporaries were celebrating a positive liberal future, &lt;em&gt;DS9&lt;/em&gt; was suggesting that even in a utopia, there were margins where people could fall. During the 90s it didn’t find it’s audience, but in the 21st century Trekkies found that it’s relevance was very persistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It posed a similar variety of the premise bending questions that &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; did. “What would the Federation going to war look like?” Because of all the oblique references to conflicts past in &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; shows, we never had actually seen them. &lt;em&gt;Deep Space Nine&lt;/em&gt; became a favorite among fans because it critically examines how a brave new world survives existential challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regrettably fans are rarely articulate, and studios tend to take the simplest of messages from any feedback that filters through to them. The aspects of &lt;em&gt;Deep Space Nine&lt;/em&gt; that ought to be repeated are the complicated moral dilemmas the characters face, and the strong sense of continuity across the series. Unfortunately the takeaway that the studios seemed to get was that “&lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; should be a war show.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last few years, many have seen &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; devolve into a mere action adventure franchise. People pine for a more character oriented and cerebral story. But lest we forget, it wasn’t JJ Abrams that brought us here. The franchise wasn’t hijacked by interlopers and forced into it’s current state. Many otherwise respected writers made these decisions because they thought it’s what the audience wanted. It was a decision that we all participated in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Next Generation&lt;/em&gt; didn’t have a massive budget. They were able to have a few tentpole episodes that featured vast interstellar phenomenon, and maybe some photon torpedoes. But many episodes were made cheaply. In some, they slid into the backlot of the holodeck. But in others, they relied on character based drama. &lt;em&gt;The Drumhead&lt;/em&gt; very clearly stands out in this category. And even in a mid-budget show like &lt;em&gt;The Inner Light&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Next Generation&lt;/em&gt; tended to shine the brightest when telling simple yet profound stories. They did have Patrick Steward giving vigorous story notes, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The series ended with &lt;em&gt;All Good Things&lt;/em&gt;, a perfect blend of intellectual conundrum and action. Then it transitioned to film. I liked &lt;em&gt;Generations&lt;/em&gt; more than most. But when I was thirteen, &lt;em&gt;First Contact&lt;/em&gt; hit theaters. And that proved to be a concept defining entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The massive space battle against the Borg at the beginning of &lt;em&gt;First Contact&lt;/em&gt; was everything I had dreamed about since watching the series. Dozens of starships! Suddenly the scale of the universe wasn’t just alluded to, we were seeing it! It was an emotionally satisfying film that also had the budget to foreground its action elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet it seemed that the notion that &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; films should feature a large amount of action is what stuck with the Producers. Special effects technology had reached a point where convincing space battles were much cheaper to produce. &lt;em&gt;Insurrection&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Nemesis&lt;/em&gt; both contain some pretty potent conceptual material at their core, but they’re bogged down with action sequences that largely hinder the plot and character development. By all accounts, the amount of dialogue removed from the final cut of &lt;em&gt;Nemesis&lt;/em&gt; was equivalent to the length of the giant superfluous space battle at the end of the film. To keep themselves in a studio approved two hour run time, they were removing a lot of the conceptual meat and substituting explosions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the small screen, &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt; was encountering much the same problem. Brannon Braga was working on autopilot, and to be charitable, he was probably burning out after over a decade on the franchise. He fell back to using the same formulas that were alienating audiences on the big screen, with the thought that it’s what the audiences wanted. The show was prioritizing the action elements of the series, and any kind of cohesive philosophy was largely absent. By the time Manny Coto took over and tried to change direction, it was too late. The audience had burned out too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revisions that JJ Abrams provided were not his doing alone. Most of what he is criticized for were started by the long time Producers of Trek. They had spent years sailing the ship in that direction. Abrams simply fulfilled the trend Rick Berman and company started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These films have their own structural problems. They are often heavily rooted in Earth and recognizable locations. They seem to revolve around vast and dire threats that are personified in a single individual bent on revenge. And, oh yeah, you can say this as much about the &lt;em&gt;Next Generation&lt;/em&gt; films as you can about the JJ Abrams versions. “Remember when we used to be explorers?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theonion.com/video/trekkies-bash-new-star-trek-film-as-fun-watchable-14333&quot;&gt;an Onion video&lt;/a&gt;: “Yes it was exciting. But where was the heavy handed message about tolerance?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a funny joke, but ultimately most &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; fans like &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; because it’s like &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;. What the studio lost sight of is that the most profitable entries of the franchise had strong moral components that were then balanced with the spectacle. But the notion that a “good” movie has crossover appeal is hard to replicate. Instead, Paramount had found that putting a &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; layer of paint on an otherwise generic action franchise was just as profitable as anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an ironic reversal from where &lt;em&gt;The Next Generation&lt;/em&gt; was 25 years ago, I think that &lt;em&gt;Star Trek: Discovery&lt;/em&gt; runs the risk of studio notes inquiring where the explosions are, rather than saying there are too many explosions. It’s a noticeably high budget show, and and I can see an executive getting perturbed that the bulk of an episode is set in a briefing room or science lab. But ultimately that’s the notion of &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; that people have been buying for over twenty years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do hope that &lt;em&gt;Discovery&lt;/em&gt; is not fated to be overwhelmed by superfluous action. I understand why they started out the series that way. But they’ve also set up a great deal of potential character development and moral conflicts that I strongly feel will play out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of what we’ve seen so far in &lt;em&gt;Discovery&lt;/em&gt; seems to be self-consciously trying to remedy the worst cliches in the franchise. First and foremost is that of diversity. Gene Roddenberry talked a lot about how the Starship Enterprise was “Starship Earth.” Well for most of the franchise, the ships seem suspiciously rooted in North American backgrounds. What we’ve seen so far is a step in the right direction to changing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second issue the writers of &lt;em&gt;Discovery&lt;/em&gt; seem to be trying to address is that of how much the characters struggle to advance their careers. We’re told that they’re the best and the brightest, but it tends to seem to frivolously effortless. There’s no drama in the best people being on the best ship surrounded by the best colleagues. One of the most poignant episodes of &lt;em&gt;The Next Generation&lt;/em&gt; was &lt;em&gt;Lower Decks&lt;/em&gt;, in which they detailed junior officers struggling to complete assignments and gain promotion. It was a glimpse at the notion that it isn’t just a set group of seven people who solve all the problems, and it reminded us that the protagonists at one point did struggle to get to where they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, I started kicking around ideas for how I’d write a new &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; show. One of my ideas was to start the protagonist off as First Officer. After a few seasons, I would kill off the Captain, and the First Officer would take command. So suffice to say when they kill off Captain Lorca in Discovery and promote Michael Burnam to command the Discovery, I expect to receive a royalty check!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an aside, this attempt to remedy these previous shortcomings created what I see as the only significant misstep in the two opening episodes. In a vision of an ostensibly utopian future, we saw a very 21st century depiction of the smartest person on the ship get her ideas roundly rejected from every quarter. And at the end of it all, when she was right about everything, she gets imprisoned for it. I have faith that &lt;em&gt;Discovery&lt;/em&gt; is going to do great things with this character and this story. I think &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; needed to do more to show its main characters struggle. I think &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; needs a black woman in the lead. But ending the premiere episodes on the note of marginalization and incarceration of a black woman in a utopian was difficult to stomach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The series has already telegraphed what it’s going to be about. They’ve already been forthright that there’s a difference between race and culture. We have antagonists who are motivated by a religious zeal. They see pluralism and diversity as a threat. We have a protagonist who was scarred by a terror attack by that group twenty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about what Star Trek means, and the ways it has gone in the past. In &lt;em&gt;Day of the Dove&lt;/em&gt;, the last original series representation of the Klingons, Kirk allies with Kang and the Klingons to drive out a hostile life form. In &lt;em&gt;The Undiscovered Country&lt;/em&gt;, Kirk abandons his own bitterness over the death of his son. The power to overcome prejudice and the power to forgive is a utopian narrative. The world we live in now needs a road map that shows how people can break away from hate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek: Discovery&lt;/em&gt; has positioned itself to question and critique the Liberal values that have driven the franchise, and quite possibly the colonialist subtext of the Federation too. This is absolutely a story that &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; needs to be telling in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/2017/star-trek-discovery-bridge.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/star-trek-discovery-bridge.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jesse</name></author><category term="Discovery" /><category term="Klingons" /><category term="Michael Burnham" /><summary type="html">I’ve watched the opening episodes of Star Trek: Discovery twice, and I’m heartily on board. There’s something fundamentally relieving about having Star Trek on the air again.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Cage Revisited</title><link href="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/the-cage-revisited/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Cage Revisited" /><published>2017-09-20T17:12:43-07:00</published><updated>2017-09-20T17:12:43-07:00</updated><id>http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/the-cage-revisited</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/the-cage-revisited/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/the-cage.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, the original Star Trek series was the only on television at 1:30am Sunday mornings. As a fan of The Next Generation and the movies, I was intensely curious, but opportunities for viewing were limited. However, the local Blockbuster had a copy of The Cage, Gene Roddenberry’s original, unaired pilot episode. As a result, I’ve probably seen that more than any other episode of the original.
&lt;!--more--&gt;
As an adult, I have a complicated relationship with it. On the one hand, I love the characters. Pike was so well drawn that the franchise just hasn’t been able to give him up. Number One rightly became an icon to feminist fans, and the series would have been better with her in it. And of course the episode marked the first appearance of the Enterprise, Mister Spock. The theme was terrific. I know the mythos is that NBC rejected it because it was “too cerebral,” but I suspect they didn’t like the scathing critique of media culture!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, it has its problems. Roddenberry’s intergalactic space ship seems to be rooted in World War II American destroyers. Gender issues. And the portrayal of technology and the broader culture is inconsistent with the franchise to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s my version. I was surprised by how much I added and changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my updated version of crew biographies from Roddenberry’s original pitch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain Christina Pike — The skipper, about thirty-four, Academy graduate, rank of Captain. Lean and capable, both mentally and physically. A colorfully complex personality, she is capable of action and decision which can verge on the heroic—and at the same time lives a continual battle with self-doubt and the loneliness of command. As with similar commanders and explorers of the past, her primary weakness is a predilection to action over administration, a temptation to take the greatest risks onto herself. But, unlike most explorers of Earth history, she has an almost compulsive compassion for the plight of others, alien as well as human, and must continually fight the temptation to risk many to save one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Executive Officer — Never referred to as anything but “Number One,” the second in command of the Enterprise is perpetually calm and collected. Like many natives of Alpha Centauri, she has a look that belies any easy 21st century assessment of age or ethnicity. An extraordinarily efficient officer, “Number One” enjoys the fact that she is probably Pike’s superior in the detailed knowledge of the multiple equipment systems, departments, and crew members aboard the vessel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Navigator — Ana Zepeda is constantly reminding her peers that her family has been serving in Starfleet for four generations, dating back to the N.X. program. As a result, she serves as the amateur historian of the Enterprise, enthusiastically regaling the crew with tales of the hidden wonders of the Milky Way after hours in the Mess Hall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ship’s Doctor — Philip Boyce, an unlikely space traveler. At the age of fifty-one, he’s worldly, humorously cynical, and makes it a point to thoroughly enjoy his own weaknesses. Captain Pike’s only real confidant, Boyce considers himself the only realist aboard, measures each new landing in terms of relative annoyance, rather than excitement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Science Officer — The first Vulcan to graduate Starfleet Academy, Mr. Spock devotes himself entirely to the pursuit of knowledge. The son of the Planet Vulcan’s ambassador to Earth and a human schoolteacher, Spock is torn between two worlds: the stern discipline of Vulcan logic and the emotionalism of his human heritage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chief of Operations — The working level commander of all the ship’s functions from manning the bridge to supervising the lowliest scrub detail. Colt is the fresh from the Academy, and is reputed to be the youngest bridge officer in the fleet. He is simultaneously eager to prove himself, and intimidated by the stature of his new captain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B9zxKQnAC0c7LUJXamk5SlhZVk0&quot;&gt;You can read the full script here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jesse</name></author><category term="Original Series" /><category term="Pike" /><category term="Spock" /><category term="The Cage" /><summary type="html">When I was a kid, the original Star Trek series was the only on television at 1:30am Sunday mornings. As a fan of The Next Generation and the movies, I was intensely curious, but opportunities for viewing were limited. However, the local Blockbuster had a copy of The Cage, Gene Roddenberry’s original, unaired pilot episode. As a result, I’ve probably seen that more than any other episode of the original.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In college, Ben Shapiro worked to undermine Free Speech.</title><link href="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/ben-shapiro-free-speech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In college, Ben Shapiro worked to undermine Free Speech." /><published>2017-09-11T10:54:36-07:00</published><updated>2017-09-11T10:54:36-07:00</updated><id>http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/ben-shapiro-free-speech</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/ben-shapiro-free-speech/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/ben-shapiro.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With his coming talk at UC Berkeley, Ben Shapiro has been a much discussed subject on social media. Why would people object to Shapiro?
&lt;!--more--&gt;
Among his other work, Shapiro has been an editor for Brietbart. That site has heavily contributed to contemporary racial animus, heavily distorting facts to fit their bigoted agenda. While Shapiro was employed there as an editor, they developed a very cohesive editorial policy that narrativized news and politics well beyond individual stories. The conclusions that Shapiro and his writers very strongly point to is that criminal justice reform is actively dangerous to white people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are very adept at staying one step inside the realm of plausible deniability when it comes to actively promoting racism. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/08/16/magazine/breitbart-alt-right-steve-bannon.html&quot;&gt;Brietbart’s readings of news, politics, and even history&lt;/a&gt; point to the idea that black people have historically deserved what have happened to them; that attempts to reduce recidivism that doesn’t simply involve more incarceration is doomed to fail; and that root causes of crime is entirely unrelated to chronic, multi-generational poverty, but instead is rooted in blackness. White nationalists have gotten the message loud and clear, flocking to the site. The rhetoric in their comment section is largely indistinguishable from Stormfront, an actual Nazi website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon further researching Shapiro himself, I stumbled upon the fact that he too went to UCLA. A fellow Bruin, he graduated the year I transferred in. I’ve been looking through his old columns at the Daily Bruin, and he seems overwhelmingly preoccupied with people smoking weed. Tattoos, piercings, and a local sex shop, seemed to preoccupy his regular scrutiny in his column. As someone who inherited his campus, I have to say that most of the people I encountered were entirely normal folks just living average college student lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s striking are his claims that certain Professors endorse murder, and they teach that to their students. In “&lt;a href=&quot;http://dailybruin.com/2001/11/19/effects-of-campus-liberalism-f/&quot;&gt;Effects of campus liberalism far-reaching&lt;/a&gt;,” Shapiro takes the cases of Sarah Jane Olsen and Mumia Abu Jamal, and finds Professors who have publicly supported their attempts to gain a fair trial for the former, and attempts to have their case retried for the latter. Shapiro concludes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These are the people who will shape the youth of this country.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;These are the men and women who will forge college students into&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;adults. They excuse murder. They promote terrorism. They&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;stretch their arms toward their vulnerable students, leading them&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;into moral oblivion. This is not a free speech issue; free speech&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;cannot justify the willful endorsement of murder. This is an issue&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;of good versus evil.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a particularly far reaching statement. Stating a belief that someone was wrongfully convicted is not an apologia for murder. And in the column, Shapiro only mentions activities that have taken place outside of the classroom. He entirely fails to even attempt to prove his claim that these Professors were injecting ideology into their classes. For all his assertions about UCLA being a hostile space for conservatism, it appears as though the Daily Bruin gave him free reign to print borderline libelous material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, if someone went and dug up what I had been writing in 2001, it would probably not be able to pass muster either. But that paragraph got me thinking about a notorious incident at UCLA in 2006 that made the national news. I’ve done some digging, and Ben Shapiro was involved in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, a recent graduate named Andrew Jones started the “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bruinalumni.com/&quot;&gt;Bruin Alumni Association&lt;/a&gt;,” as a conservative alternative to the officially sanctioned UCLA Alumni Association. As one can still see on its website, it had a political bent from its inception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thenation.com/article/uclas-dirty-thirty/&quot;&gt;Jones had made waves before&lt;/a&gt;. “He made news for running an affirmative action bake sale, in which he charged white male students more for cookies than minorities and women. Jones worked for Horowitz, but according to the New York Times, Horowitz says he fired him because Jones pressured students to ‘file false reports that they had been physically attacked by leftists.’ “&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was the creation of the list of “Dirty Thirty” Professors at UCLA that brought him to the forefront of his alma mater. &lt;a href=&quot;http://articles.latimes.com/2006/jan/18/local/me-ucla18&quot;&gt;As reported by the LA Times&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The year-old Bruin Alumni Assn. says its “Exposing UCLA’s Radical Professors” initiative takes aim at faculty “actively proselytizing their extreme views in the classroom, whether or not the commentary is relevant to the class topic.” Although the group says it is concerned about radical professors of any political stripe, it has named an initial “Dirty 30” of teachers it identifies with left-wing or liberal causes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some of the instructors mentioned accuse the association of conducting a witch hunt that threatens to harm the teaching atmosphere, and at least one of the group’s advisory board members has resigned because he considers the bounty offers inappropriate. The university said it will warn the association that selling copies of professors’ lectures would violate campus rules and raise copyright issues.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jones’ group is following in the footsteps of various conservative groups that have taken steps, including monitoring professors, to counter what they regard as an overwhelming leftist tilt at elite colleges and universities around the country. He said many of these efforts, however, have done a poor job of documenting their claims. As a result, Jones, said, the Bruin Alumni Assn. is offering to pay students for tapes and notes from classes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We’re just trying to get people back on a professional level of things. Having been a student myself up until 2003, and then watching what other students like myself have gone through, I’m very concerned about the level of professional teaching at UCLA,” said Jones, who said he is supporting himself with a modest salary from the organization and is its only full-time employee.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“He said he plans to show what he considers biased material to professors and administrators and seek to have teachers present more balanced lectures or possibly face reprimand.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the website itself is defunct, and I’ve been unable to find a complete version of its contents online. In addition, I’ve been unable to definitively find contact information for Jones to clarify the above statement. But as it stands, it seems that Jones wished to professionally damage professors who presented information that Jones himself found ideologically objectionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://vnnforum.com/showthread.php?t=28917&quot;&gt;fullest version of the list currently available online can be found here&lt;/a&gt;. Be warned, this is a Neo-Nazi discussion board, so I wouldn’t access it at work. Racist and anti-semitic slurs abound. And it should also be noted that they’re largely supportive of Jones’s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally took classes in 2005 from two of the targeted Professors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took Professor Katherine King’s Ancient Epic course in the Classics Department. This is what Jones had to say about her:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Given the promising start of an arrest at a 1990 anti-military aid protest, the ‘90s were a surprisingly tame decade for King. Sure, there were affirmative action protests, in fact, quite a lot of them, but by 2004, King was reduced to the status of bystander as a new generation of hotheads made their political mark. While it’s late in her career, King needs to execute a turn-around, and quick, lest she relinquish her radical ranking altogether.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course this is a truncated version; in its final form, I clearly recall reading an indignant mention that Professor King was a Feminist. Yet Professor King kept her class entirely free of contemporary political content. I had three roommates who took the course with me who can corroborate this. We discussed Homer and Virgil, and concepts critical to understanding Ancient Greek literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in the above indictment of her political activities, Jones never claimed that Professor King actually brought her politics into her classroom. Nevertheless, the fact that she held ideas as a private citizen was apparently objectionable enough to prompt Jones to attempt to pay money to launch a private investigation of her classroom, hoping to gain information that would lead to her career being damaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took Professor James Gelvin’s course on the Israeli-Palestinian conflict in the Political Science Department. Here’s his entry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slammed early and often for his biased Palestinian classroom proselytizing, Gelvin remains a threat for the top five based on sheer fervor alone. As they say on SportsCenter, you can’t stop James Gelvin, you can only hope to contain him.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the class to be a remarkably even-handed primer on a controversial topic. Again, I took the course with former roommates who can corroborate this. If Jones ever found a controversial incident he never related it in print. If anyone in his organization ever found a flaw in any of Gelvin’s published works on the subject, they never presented it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a lecture course with no formal discussion section. Yet one of the things that Gelvin did before every class was to arrive thirty minutes before the start, smoke a large tobacco pipe, and talk with his students. He attracted quite a following. It should be noted that attendees of these informal discussion sections included both Muslims and Jews, and that Gelvin functioned as a moderator, keeping discussions productive and respectful. I’m unsure what about this free exchange of ideas the Bruin Alumni Association and its board found so odious. It appears that in their view, nothing less than rigid adherence to pro-Israeli orthodoxy ought to exempt a Professor from being investigated for professional sanction by the University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does Ben Shapiro have to do with any of this? He was on the board of directors for the Bruin Alumni Association. His endorsement still appears on their website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/2017/Bruin-Alumni-Association.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/Bruin-Alumni-Association.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the “Dirty Thirty” list and the Bruin Alumni Association started to receive blowback from prominent conservatives, four board members left the organization, citing the potentially chilling effect these tactics might have on academic freedom. Not Shapiro. He doubled down on his support. He was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ocregister.com/2006/01/20/ucla-alumni-fallout-spreads/&quot;&gt;briefly quoted by the Orange County Register&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Another board member, Ben Shapiro, said he was happy about the tape-recording payment plan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shapiro, who wrote the 2004 book “Brainwashed” based on notes he took of UCLA professors he felt were inappropriately one-sided, said tape-recording was “the next logical step.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What’s good about this is then it’s not a he-said, she-said kind of thing.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At no point did the Bruin Alumni Association enumerate what they considered acceptable discourse in a classroom. They did not disseminate guidelines for how to remain ideologically acceptable. And in outlining desired next steps, they discussed in the vaguest of terms how they would submit Professors who diverged from their standards of acceptable ideology to the University for official sanction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course this all happened when Shapiro and Jones were in their early twenties. They were clearly upset by a campus culture of people having fun and valuing things differently than them. In all their articles for the Daily Bruin, they can only point to feelings of alienation, rather than any concrete incidences of marginalization in their college careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s look back at Shapiro’s earlier article. He called for the firing of Professors who, in their time as private citizens and not in the classroom, thought that certain radicals charged with crimes were being unfairly treated by the justice system. He wanted them fired for their beliefs. And his involvement with the Bruin Alumni Association was similarly suspect. They did not advocate for more inclusion, more dialogue, and more speech. Instead they stated that instructors who did not meet their vague standards of classroom conduct should be punished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern iteration of the Free Speech movement needs to recognize how much they are being astroturfed by the far right. People like Shapiro see Free Speech not as a noble ideological goal, but instead as one of the only venues where their openly hateful views are regarded as socially acceptable. As indicated by the above, Shapiro has historically been quite open to the idea of silencing discourse they personally disagree with.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jesse</name></author><category term="academic freedom" /><category term="ben shapiro" /><category term="brietbart" /><category term="Free Speech" /><category term="ucla" /><summary type="html">With his coming talk at UC Berkeley, Ben Shapiro has been a much discussed subject on social media. Why would people object to Shapiro?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Political Violence.</title><link href="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/political-violence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Political Violence." /><published>2017-09-03T06:59:37-07:00</published><updated>2017-09-03T06:59:37-07:00</updated><id>http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/political-violence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/09/political-violence/">&lt;p&gt;It’s incredible the kind of sanitized version of activism Americans believed existed before the modern day. Unions and Suffragettes started fires and planted bombs. They engaged in civil disobedience and had to be ready to defend themselves against both fellow citizens and police. In the Civil Rights movement, the Freedom Riders and lunch counter sit-ins were all violating local law, and defending themselves when brawling did break out was not unheard of. In one of the clearest through lines from violence to results, the gay rights movement didn’t start getting taken seriously until they started throwing bricks at cops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Charlottesville was a good example of why people who counter-protest white supremacists ought to be prepared to fight back. The Nazis talked beforehand how they were planning on killing people, and they did, and they were recorded afterwards saying they were happy that they killed someone. Brawls broke out, with Nazis making no distinction between people who wanted to counter-protest non-violently, and the people who were ready to meet their violence. Even as Nazis fired pistols at counter-protesters, the Police did not intervene. If you’ve read up on the history of protest movements—or even look at contemporary events—you’ll see that law enforcement as a whole is largely disinterested in keeping leftists safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the people who came out to Berkeley the other week had good intentions. Even the ones dressed in black and wearing masks. That being said, it does not appear there was provocation for some of the more jarring altercations filmed and shared through social media. 7000 people showing up to disrupt what had been a planned white supremacist rally was an effective enough counter. If a lone Nazi takes a swing at you, sometimes you have to take a black eye to control the narrative of the event. I wear my suit at political actions for such eventualities. But Berkeley wasn’t the first time I’ve had to contend with rowdy people just looking to fight or break stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2003 there would always be a contingent of black bloc who would come to any protest. At a certain point they would peel away from the main group and start smashing things. This was annoying on two levels: first, it entirely undermined the nonviolent nature of our message. Two, it was entirely misdirected; trying to disrupt the process of the war using violent means could have been at least an understandable political act. Indiscriminate and omnidirectional violence, however, would dominate the headlines and derail the message the protesters were actually trying to send.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve spent the last 15 years complaining about black bloc tactics, because they’ve often seemed to me to be young people using a legitimate event as cover to start illegitimate violence. But the critical thing to remember is that leftist protest movements are not unique in this. People go to music events looking to start a fight at any provocation. There’s literally a widely used phrase, “football hooliganism,” used to describe people who go to sporting events looking for a fight. The FBI has had a long running investigation of police organizations being infiltrated by white supremacists, and plenty of cops join for the wrong reason besides. The military, Islamic religious organizations, the list goes on. They all have Those Assholes. I’m going to assert that there’s a problem with people seeking institutional cover for petty violence that transcends leftist protest movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why doesn’t the left more vocally denounce such violence? Well there’s a lot of denunciations of a lot of violence that does go on. We spend a lot of time denouncing war, and the death of civilians. The major cause that the left has been rallying around the last several years has been the extrajudicial murder of unarmed black people by the police. But you know what? It’s really hard to take critiques seriously from people who spend more time wringing their hands about broken windows than dead people. And any kind of well meaning public self reflection tends to be seized upon by conservatives, taken entirely out of context, and used as a cudgel to discredit notions of social justice as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Americans in general need to address their culture of violence. The most tenaciously persistent trope in our cinema, particularly those directly marketed at men, is the notion that emotional catharsis and resolution only comes after a fight. People who are left in their politics are just as prone to internalizing that message as much as anyone else.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jesse</name></author><category term="black bloc" /><summary type="html">It’s incredible the kind of sanitized version of activism Americans believed existed before the modern day. Unions and Suffragettes started fires and planted bombs. They engaged in civil disobedience and had to be ready to defend themselves against both fellow citizens and police. In the Civil Rights movement, the Freedom Riders and lunch counter sit-ins were all violating local law, and defending themselves when brawling did break out was not unheard of. In one of the clearest through lines from violence to results, the gay rights movement didn’t start getting taken seriously until they started throwing bricks at cops.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Charlottesville, Dunkirk, and “The Good War”</title><link href="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/08/charlottesville-dunkirk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Charlottesville, Dunkirk, and &quot;The Good War&quot;" /><published>2017-08-12T16:56:17-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-12T16:56:17-07:00</updated><id>http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/08/charlottesville-dunkirk</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/08/charlottesville-dunkirk/">&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, people have been critiquing the film Dunkirk for its lack of portrayal of colonial soldiers during the evacuation of British forces from France in 1940. This is certainly not without merit; British infantry was not segregated by race, with soldiers from the Caribbean serving in the Infantry alongside soldiers from the British Isles themselves. Ultimately the film focuses on three (and a half, exposition squirrel Branagh) narratives. It does not intend to be an all-encompassing view of the battle. Still, this criticism does bear weight, particularly in light of what virtually every other narrative of the Second World War leaves out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the film I saw a trailer for Darkest Hour, an upcoming film by Joe Wright, that covers the same events from the perspective of Winston Churchill. If the preview is any indication, it seems to follow the course of many other depictions of Churchill, as a noble and pugnacious man standing up against the forces of evil. And while he was consistently opposed to Fascism, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/politics/not-his-finest-hour-the-dark-side-of-winston-churchill-2118317.html&quot;&gt;there were other aspects of his career that do not get equal coverage&lt;/a&gt;. As a young man, he participated in suppressing a native revolt in Sudan; he served as a journalist during the Boer War, yet remained curiously apathetic as both black Africans and the Boers themselves were rounded up and placed in concentration camps. He remained as violently opposed to Indian Independence as he was to Fascism, suggesting that the British Viceroy in India crush Mohandas Gandhi to death with an Elephant. And later in his career as Prime Minister, he supported violent suppression against countries around the world which were trying to gain freedom from the British.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re from England, there are lots of books and movies that can help you feel great about what your grandfather did during the War. From Dunkirk to Normandy, there are countless narratives about how the resolute, Democracy loving Anglo-Americans fight back against the forces of German darkness. But in all the movies I’ve seen about the War, very few have seen fit to mention that the campaign in North Africa was one collection of Empires reconquering their territory from the upstart, insurgent collection of Empires. In the Anglo-American world, people are not seriously asked to question this. Arabs and Africans often occupy the distant periphery of these stories that take place in their own countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today in response to the riots in Charlottesville, many white Liberals are decrying that the violence by white supremacists there “isn’t America,” and “we fought a whole war to settle this.” Well, it isn’t nearly as simple as that. In 1984, Studs Terkel published his Pulitzer winning examination of World War Two, told from many of the common people that fought it. The title wasn’t meant to be taken literally; it was laced with very deliberate irony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the stories that Terkel told unfolded five miles from where my parents were raised, and where I was born. On July 17, 1944, munitions bound for the Pacific were being loaded at the Port Chicago Naval Magazine, just north of Concord, California. The laborers were insufficiently trained, the safety procedures were inadequate, and the workers were lied to about the how volatile the explosives they were loading were. In the ensuing explosion, 320 men at the dock were killed. 202 of them were African American.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/Portchicago2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Picture showing the wreckage at Port Chicago&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up hearing stories of my Grandfather’s bravery on board the destroyer U.S.S. Radford during the war. He served with distinction in the South Pacific, arming the weapons that were very likely supplied by some of the same men who died during the Port Chicago explosion. The stories of him fighting fascism was in no small way enabled by the fact that these black men were exploited at home, at the eventual cost of their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply “fighting fascism” during the 1940s isn’t an automatic vindication of a person’s principles. George Wallace, one of the most notorious segregationist politicians in America, flew in the Army Air Corps. People who grew up attending lynchings and benefitting from segregation could easily tell themselves that they were combatting German expansionism if they were stationed in Europe, or continue to spin white supremacist justifications for fighting the Japanese. After all, the Phillipines were an American colony; indeed, most of the region had been divided among European powers, only to be conquered by the Japanese. It isn’t a stretch to read the war in the Pacific as a reassertion of European and American hegemony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I’m very glad that National Socialists were thrown out of power in Germany. How many films in the West are devoted to the Russians and their role? Or the massive drain that Chinese armies put on Japanese resources? It’s so ironic that an entire spectrum of modern politics is dedicated to defiantly saying “fuck your feelings,” yet meticulously maintains a false narrative of the past where they get to continue to feel unambiguously great about the things their community and nation have done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was raised in a white, suburban environment. The problem with Liberals like me is that they look on the past with split vision. They see a war of liberation sweep the world in their films, but don’t internalize that most people in the world remained unfree for decades thereafter, including Black people living in America. When white kids were watching Leave it to Beaver, the French were killing in Vietnam, and black men in Alabama were being sentenced to death for the pettiest of crimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to live in an America that stands for Liberty, Justice, and Equality. But the problem is that those are values that actively have to be fought for. White people heard, “The arc of the moral universe is long, but it bends toward justice,” and thought it absolved them of actually doing the grueling work required to effect that change, and make that a reality. For many Liberals, the work required to effect that change seemed as distant as any movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today white supremacists, agitating for the removal of the people they deem inferior, murdered at least one person who was counter-protesting said ideas. The “times that try men’s souls” may feel immediate now, but they have never left us. Silence and inaction now are just as much complicity as they have ever been. “It’s 2017” shouldn’t be a cry for how civilized we ought to be; it should be an anguished wail for how much work remains undone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jesse</name></author><category term="Imperialism" /><category term="Racism" /><category term="segregation" /><category term="World War II" /><summary type="html">In recent weeks, people have been critiquing the film Dunkirk for its lack of portrayal of colonial soldiers during the evacuation of British forces from France in 1940. This is certainly not without merit; British infantry was not segregated by race, with soldiers from the Caribbean serving in the Infantry alongside soldiers from the British Isles themselves. Ultimately the film focuses on three (and a half, exposition squirrel Branagh) narratives. It does not intend to be an all-encompassing view of the battle. Still, this criticism does bear weight, particularly in light of what virtually every other narrative of the Second World War leaves out.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">War is Failure.</title><link href="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/08/war-is-failure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="War is Failure." /><published>2017-08-07T09:32:39-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-07T09:32:39-07:00</updated><id>http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/08/war-is-failure</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/08/war-is-failure/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today is Purple Heart Day. The best way to honor those who have sacrificed is to ensure that future generations do not have to bear the same horrors.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/normandy-dead-germans.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second time in as many weeks, I’ve seen a Conservative figure wax nostalgic about World War II. First it was Nigel Farage, talking in vague terms about Dunkirk, and lost American honor. And this morning, Joe Scarborough tweeted, “Young men in the 1940s liberated Europe from Nazism and the Pacific from the Japanese Empire. Today, too many stay home playing video games.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;img--centered&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/newspapers.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&quot;All of this modern technology is making us antisocial!&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes Joe, everyone knows that in 1939 there was a Xbox in every store window, and it was just the fundamental moral toughness of that generation that led them to actually go and get their leg blown off by a howitzer in Europe rather than just play World War II in Call of Duty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Scarborough’s really weird insistence that what this generation needs is a good old fashioned war to toughen them up deserves scrutiny. The “greatest generation” didn’t achieve that title because they willingly threw themselves into fixing the world’s problems. People like my grandparents were instead dealt the worst possible hands by their parents or grandparents’ generation. They did what they had to because they literally had no other choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s unpack all of this. The “Great War” was purely elective. It was a system of Imperial powers who measured their pride and self worth with how much of the map had their little flag displayed on it. Older empires like Austria and Russia wanted to expand their stake. The largest and most successful, France and Britain, wanted to defend their stake. And the rising empire Germany sought to drastically expand their stake. Nationalism has been one of the most malignantly harmful forces of the modern world. And it was exclusively at play here. The leadership of Europe, en masse, decided that their own petty pride was worth more than the lives of their children. At best, they thought that they could massacre their fellow Europeans as efficiently as they had massacred natives in their colonies around the world. Instead, the horrors they had inflicted on Africa and Asia for generations was now visited on their own children and grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The First World War did not end in a grand battle. After years of starvation and brutal combat, the people of Central and Eastern Europe rose in revolt, throwing of the yoke of Authoritarianism. But in Britain and France, the leadership chose not to embrace their newly freed fellows in Democracy. Georges Clemenceau and David Lloyd George opted for revanchism instead. They pushed for a peace that would fatally cripple any government that willingly signed it. The new German “Weimar” Republic, run by civilians who had not pushed their country into war the way the Prussian aristocracy had, briefly considered a resumption of hostilities to avoid signing something that would cripple their Democracy. But they could not imagine a resumption of the carnage. They signed, and their children were doomed to another round of carnage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Asia, Japan was only emboldened by these events. Russia and Germany were no longer potential rivals in the East. They began to more aggressively expand at the expense of their neighbors. America wasn’t concerned about massacred civilians in China; for them the prime moral imperatives were their own colonial possessions in the Philippines and Pacific islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Germany, the same generals who had counseled the Weimar government to seek peace with the Allies now disavowed and denied their own actions. One of the most significant factors that led to the rise of Fascism in Germany was that Hindenburg and Ludendorff started loudly asserting that the war was in fact winnable, and that the betrayal of both leftist insurgents and the new Republic at home had caused them to surrender. It should be noted that Erich Ludendorff was an early convert to the Nazi Party, and Paul von Hindenburg, as the President of the Republic his so thoroughly despised, named Adolf Hitler chancellor in 1933.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Greatest Generation” were themselves saddled with the Great Depression. It must be noted that economic contractions happen largely independently of environmental factors. Men don’t spontaneously decide to stop working en masse. A region going arid or a vein of ore running dry does not cripple an entire economy. Instead, economic downturns are decisions that people with economic power make, when they decide that the preservation of the value of their own wealth is more important than the welfare of their fellow citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On virtually every level, the Second World War was preventable. Embracing Nationalist expansionism was a choice. Embracing a policy of bitter revenge instead of nation building after the First World War was a choice. Embracing free market economic policies that lead to inequality and instability was a choice. These were all mistakes that were made when the young men fighting in France in 1940 were children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conservatives have seen too many movies. Piers Morgan recently tweeted, “Can you imagine if social media existed during WW2? This generation is so absurdly soft by comparison to my grandparents’ era. Toughen up!” It’s an interesting perspective from someone who never served in the military. Indeed, during the Gulf War, Joe Scarborough was enjoying life in an air conditioned office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our world is heading towards other calamities as great as the Second World War. Manmade Climate Change itself promises to transform our way of life as profoundly as any other factor in recent history. Yet the people in charge of our country are steadfastly committed that they will do nothing to mitigate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others have speculated that with the current resurgence of right wing nationalism, our planet is heading towards another great calamity of mass war. If such a bloodletting occurs, the current generation of young people will bear it as young people have always borne the dreams of carnage visited on them by their fathers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Piers Morgan or Nigel Farage talk about war, they don’t imagine their own children, let alone themselves fighting in it. They don’t picture themselves burying the 60,000 corpses of young sons that littered the fields of France in 1940. They can only imagine themselves sitting in their comfortable lounges, awash in carefully curated and sanitized images of distant glory, secure in the thought that if his son cradled his dying friend in his arms, perhaps they would get along better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have made much about Joe Scarborough’s recent feud with Donald Trump. Don’t buy it. Our own warmonger President skipped out of his generation’s optional war by claiming his feet hurt. When Trump at last gets his wish, and American corpses are stacked like cordwood in Iran or North Korea, he can feel like his own youthful cowardice is vindicated. All it will take is the frivolous loss of tens of thousands young lives for men like Scarborough to fall back in line and speak in glowing terms about the state of our nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/2017/dead-of-war.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/dead-of-war_sm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jesse</name></author><category term="Joe Scarborough" /><category term="Nationalism" /><category term="Piers Morgan" /><category term="World War II" /><summary type="html">Today is Purple Heart Day. The best way to honor those who have sacrificed is to ensure that future generations do not have to bear the same horrors.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Fate of the Gracchi and the Future.</title><link href="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/07/the-fate-of-the-gracchi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fate of the Gracchi and the Future." /><published>2017-07-27T23:39:36-07:00</published><updated>2017-07-27T23:39:36-07:00</updated><id>http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/07/the-fate-of-the-gracchi</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://jessemackinnon.com/2017/07/the-fate-of-the-gracchi/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2017/gracci.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 133BC, Tiberius Gracchus was a popular politician who championed much needed land reform in the Senate. He flouted some of Rome’s unwritten traditions.&lt;!--more--&gt; One night the Optimates, that is the Party of Aristocratic, Conservative Senators, beat him and his followers to death with clubs and dumped them into the Tiber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decade later his younger brother Gaius came forward with much the same proposals, yet with slightly more modest methods. Unable to stop him, the Senate passed his legislation, yet conveniently sat idle, refusing to actually enforce it. Once again, the political order broke down, and Gaius was murdered by many of the same men who killed his brother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several decades later, a conflict arose between two Roman politicians, Marius and Sulla; here is the Roman Civil War that they have yet to make a film about. Marius the reformer was ultimately defeated by Sulla the conservative. In the aftermath, Sulla killed men at a scale previously unheard of. Ten thousand Romans lost their lives. A teenager named Gaius of the Julii was a teenager during these times, going into hiding for several months, narrowly escaping death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this young man, Julius Caesar, came into prominence as an aspiring reformer of Rome’s political system, he too came into conflict with the conservative Optimates, headed by Cato and Pompey. But unlike his Populares predecessors, he was able to outmaneuver his foes. Yet when victorious, Caesar showed clemency to the defeated faction, reinstating them in the Senate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His nephew and heir, a diligent student of history, saw what happened to his uncle. He was able to outmaneuver both foes and ostensible allies, taking full control of what was evidently becoming an Empire at 36 years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the normalization of political violence as a political tool had took root. Augustus had every single Optimate Senator murdered in short order. He had their supporters murdered. He had their children murdered. Then he was able to dismantle the political system that the conservatives had been ostensibly defending, and carrie out the remainder of his reign with a benevolent, gentle hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the Populares had been exceeding the powers of the Tribunate. But what is political murder other than a complete rejection of coming to an accommodation within a political system? In the end, the extremist, abusive mechanism that the Optimates had been using was turned against them, amplified beyond their wildest reckoning, and all their power was undone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s an important lesson we can learn from antiquity. The problem isn’t the abuse of institutions that happen today. The problem is what today’s children will grow up learning and believing is possible and normal within a political system.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>jesse</name></author><category term="Caesar" /><category term="Rome" /><summary type="html">In 133BC, Tiberius Gracchus was a popular politician who championed much needed land reform in the Senate. He flouted some of Rome’s unwritten traditions.</summary></entry></feed>